[Music]
so we are talking about value
functions okay uh people remember value
functions right we Define value
functions we said B Pi of s equal to
expected value under Pi of
right and then we Define q pi
okay good uh so now we're going to start
unrolling their
expectation so people remember this
expression right so all of you are clear
about I don't have to explain what what
is happening there again right so V Pi s
means starting in state s following
policy Pi thereafter and taking the
expectations of the the returns that I'm
getting right I'm going to start
unrolling this right so what does it
uh what does it look like so I'm going
to say V Pi of s equal to
yes
what can I write
here
huh GT +
1 right but what is what would be the
value of GT + one the expected value of
GT +
1 V Pi
of whatever state you land up in right
so let us go I'm going to say that this
is equal to V Pi of so S Prime where S
Prime is a state I'm going to land up
we'll we'll quantify S Prime in a minute
right so so people agree with me on this
right so S Prime is the state I go to
from
s right so I can take this summation and
write it like
this everybody on
board
okay great so now I did a slight slate
of hand here right so I took
GT and then I wrote it as one term plus
the expected value of GT but that is
fine because I'm anyway going to take a
expectation eventually right so this is
a slight reordering of the expectations
right inste of taking the expectation of
the full expression I took the
expectation of the inner one alone but
one thing you have to remember is it's
only a partial
expectation because S Prime can
change right so for me to get the full
expectation I need to condition on S
Prime also that is why this expression
is still inside
the expectation so if this had been the
full expectation I could have taken it
out out of the expectation since it is
still only partially conditioned so I
need to condition it on the full thing
okay so now I have to write it out so
that we'll get rid of the expectations
okay so one way of writing out this
expectation is to think of it like a
generative process
okay so remember what did they say we
are going to do we'll start in state s
right then select actions according to
policy PI right and measure
the expected return right so you're
starting in stateus and you're selecting
actions according to policy Pi so what
does it mean
okay you're using pi
right and I'm selecting actions
according to policy Pi so let us say I
picked some action a right so now what
I'm going to do I'm going to get some
reward corresponding to
that RT plus yeah the rt+ one will be
something that corresponds to that
reward so but
then before I can find out what RT +1 is
I need to specify what the next state is
going to be so I need
this so I Tak an action a and then I
determine what S Prime is and then I
determine
what right but I already determined what
S Prime is so I can do this
right so this is one step I'm taking a
pick an action a according to PI right
now that is going to cause a transition
to some S Prime according to this P that
we have there right and once I know what
the S Prime is I can figure out what the
expected reward will be as well
as V Pi S Prime because I know what S
Prime is so what is the probability that
this will be my
return is this times the probability
I'll pick action a so this whole thing
gives me the probability
that this will be
my expected
return okay so now I have to do this
over all all possible outcomes so
basically a sum over S Prime
okay is it clear how we got this
right
huh this one right so I have a sa a
right that's I picked a a first then I
pick an S Prime according to P now I
have S S Prime right so what I need to
do is figure out what this R expectation
of RT +1 would be right so that is given
in my mdp right the expectation of RT +
one would be given s a s Prime what is
the reward so that is this expectation
I've written it here expectation of R
given s s Prime right and then the
future is gamma V Pi S Prime so that S
Prime is already been fixed so I can
just add the gamma V Pi S Prime here so
the probability that this will be the
outcome right is the probability of S
Prime given S and A times the
probability of picking a given
s so all these things put together gives
me the probability that this will be the
outcome right so that is the expect Ed
outcome for one choice of a and one
choice of S Prime so I have to sum this
over all choices of S Prime and all
choices of a for me to get the overall
expectation so that's essentially what I
have done here sum over S Prime summ
over
a okay and this
is it's nice right so we written V Pi in
terms of V pi
right so this this system of it's a
system of equations right you can see
there it's a system of equations right
you have one equation for every every
state how many variables are
there number
of as many variables as there are number
of states right the number of states is
not the variable that's also fixed as
many variables as number of states and
what is the variable
here V Pi of s is the variable right so
essentially so instead of thinking of it
as a function now I can think of it as a
collection of variables right one for
each state right and I have n equations
and N
variables and can I solve
it depends on
what huh
it's
lar it's linear
huh n variables n
equations so when can you not solve
it yeah when when when yeah so you get
dependent columns and so becomes so you
have multiple Solutions and so on so
forth right so it turns out as I'll show
you in the next class right uh these
system of equations have a unique
solution
always right by virtue of the fact that
the P that you're using is
stochastic okay so the the rows of that
P Matrix will sum to one right so by
virtue of that fact we can actually go
back and show that there'll be unique
solution for this I I I just need to
write write this slightly different in a
different notation for us to see that so
I'll do that in the next class right so
this is pretty much has a unique
solution and this is uh sometimes known
as the bman equation for
VP after uh Richard belman who is one of
the Pioneers in uh the field of
stochastic dynamic
programming okay likewise you can write
a bman equation for Q
PI right s wants to tell me what the
bman equation for Q Pi would
be rest
oftion some rest of the action think of
it in a generative process right so what
is the first thing you do when you're
thinking about qsa so start with s I
pick a right I mean it's fixed so
there's no summing over there right it's
s and a is picked right so what do I
have to sum over next only the S primes
because this Pi a s is out of the
picture here right because I've already
picked a right so I don't need to I
don't need to sample from P right I
already picked a so I just start by
summing over S
Prime right now now s s Prime are all
fixed right so I can write expected
value of R given s a s
prime plus gamma
* now the interesting question is what
goes
there I could write V pi and it'll be
perfectly correct but I'll not be
writing Q Pi in terms of Q
Pi summation
over summation over all actions
[Music]
huh this a equation for Q
okay so this should also give you one
one more ancillary equation there which
is
that's the way q and V are
related and what about Q Pi can you
write Q Pi in terms of V
Pi that's exactly what what the earlier
equation was the bman equation
substitute the last summation with v pi
and that is essentially Q Pi in terms of
V
PI right so I cannot write Q Pi sa in
terms of V Pi s okay it has to be in
terms of V Pi of the subsequent
State
okay right but V Pi is I can write in
terms of Q Pi oops sorry
[Music]
[Applause]